Preliminary Guide to the S. Dillon Ripley Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
S. Dillon Ripley papers
1943-1974
MS 1066
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
The papers consist of manuscripts, typescripts, and pre-publication versions of Ripley's writings on birds of Asia and other parts of the world. Also included is film footage of Ripley's 1948 trip to Nepal.
Ripley, S. Dillon (Sidney Dillon), 1913-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of S. Dillon Ripley, 1952-1974, and A. Whitney Griswold, 1943. Transfer from Yale University Archives, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiotapes and videotapes, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Consult the finding aid and/or a reference archivist to determine availability of a use copy or the process required to generate a use copy.
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Writings are arranged chronologically by date of publication.
Biographical / Historical
Sidney Dillon Ripley was born on September 20, 1913, in New York City. He received a B.A. from Yale University in 1936 and an honorary M.A. in 1961. He earned a Ph.D. In biology from Harvard in 1943. Ripley served in the Office of Strategic Services from 1942 to 1945 and received the Order of the White Elephant and Freedom Medal from Thailand. From 1946 to 1964, he served in various capacities as professor and curator at Yale University, and was director of the Peabody Museum of Natural History from 1959 to January 1964. Ripley was secretary of the Smithsonian Institution from 1964 to 1984. He also authored several books, primarily on birds. A noted ornithologist, Ripley died on March 12, 2001.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of manuscripts, typescripts, and pre-publication versions of Ripley's writings on birds of Asia and other parts of the world. Also included is film footage of Ripley's 1948 trip to Nepal.
Birds -- Asia; Ornithologists; Zoologists; Ripley, S. Dillon (Sidney Dillon), 1913-2001
- Writings
  - On the Trail of the Money Bird
    - Manuscript and typescript drafts, [1943] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, [1943] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Search for the Spiny Babbler [typescript], 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Paddling of Ducks
    - Typescript, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Galley proofs, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Synopsis of the Birds of India, Pakistan, Ceylon, and Nepal
    - Manuscript, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unbound printed copy, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Cabinets, Lost and Found" [typescript; address before the Connecticut Academy of the Arts and Sciences], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of a book on Southeast Asia, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Footage of Ripley's trip to Nepal to film birds, [1948?]
  Biographical / Historical
  The trip was sponsored jointly by Yale University, the National Geographic Society, and the Smithsonian Institution; filmed by Howard Weaver; also has footage of ceremony with Nepal dignitaries establishing diplomatic relations with United States Ambassador Loy Henderson.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Reel 1
    - Original, 16 mm Kodachrome (Box 2)
    - Duplicating masters [color internegative; color positive], 1 (Box 2-D)
  - Reel 2
    - Original, 16 mm Kodachrome (Box 3)
    - Duplicating masters [color internegative; color positive], 1 (Box 3-D)
  - Duplicating master of reels 1 and 2, 9
- Footage of Ripley's trip to Nepal to film birds Use copy, [1948?]
  - Use copy [VHS of reels 1 and 2; with time code] (Box 2U1)
  - Use copy [VHS of reels 1 and 2; without time code] (Box 2U2)
  - Use copy of reels 1 and 2, 1 (Box 2U3)